<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copy of the articles of agreement betwixt His Highnesse Henry of Nassaw Prince of Orange, and the governour, burgers, captaines, and souldiers of the city of Breda, about the surrendring of the said city Made the 26. of Septem. 6. Octob. Faithfully translated out of the Dutch copy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118601</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853808</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853808</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19206</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01248)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19206)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 584:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copy of the articles of agreement betwixt His Highnesse Henry of Nassaw Prince of Orange, and the governour, burgers, captaines, and souldiers of the city of Breda, about the surrendring of the said city Made the 26. of Septem. 6. Octob. Faithfully translated out of the Dutch copy.</title>
                  <author>Frederick Henry, Prince of Orange, 1584-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. P[urslowe] for Nathaniel Butter; and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>18 military and 14 civil articles, both dated 7 Oct. 1637.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Breda (Netherlands) --  Siege, 1637.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19206:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19206:1"/>
            <p>The Copy of the <hi>Articles</hi> of Agreement betwixt His Highneſſe <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Governour, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Captaines, and Souldiers of the City of <hi>Breda,</hi> about the ſurrendring of the ſaid City.</p>
            <p>Made the 26. of <hi>Septem.</hi> 6. <hi>Octob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully Tranſlated out of the Dutch Copy.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E. P.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:19206:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19206:2"/>
            <head>The Copy of the <hi>Articles</hi> agreed upon, betwixt his Highneſſe the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Governour, Captaines and Souldiers within the City of <hi>Breda,</hi> about the ſurrendring of the ſaid City.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Governour of <hi>Breda,</hi> and all his military Officers, and Soldiers, of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or quality ſoever, none exempted, although they had forſaken the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Lords, the States generall, and betaken themſelves to the Cardinall Infants ſide, ſhall march thence without any let or hinderance, with their high and low Armes, bag and baggage, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of drums, diſplayed Colours, with their Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches lighted, Bullets in the mouth, as they uſe to march in war, together with all their Goods, and ſhal ſafely be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducted as far as the city of <hi>Mechelen</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II The Governour ſhall have leave to chooſe immediately 4. peeces of Ordnance, and 2. Morte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring peeces, with all their Equipage and Amunition of warre according to his owne pleaſure and mind, proportioning onely to 12. charges for every Canon.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19206:3"/>
            <p n="3">III That there ſhall be Horſes and Waggons with their drivers left unto him, ſufficient to draw the aforeſaid Artillery with their traine, to the aforenamed City of <hi>Mechlen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IIII That all Munition of warre and proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therein, late belonging to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſhall be delivered without any fraud or deceit, into the hands of ſuch as are deputed thereunto by his Highneſſe; except ſuch which was ſold before the 26. of <hi>September.</hi> the 6. of <hi>October.</hi> when the Parley was begun: But that which was ſold before, ſhall remaine to the buyer without enquiry after thoſe that have bought it.</p>
            <p n="5">V That all Officers and Souldiers as are ſicke and wounded, ſhall ſtay in the Hoſpitall or Elder-houſe ſo long till they recover againe their former health to go to <hi>Mechlen,</hi> and that then a free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy ſhalbe given unto them to carry their Armour and Baggage.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. That his Highneſſe ſhall furniſh them with Waggons and Horſes, as many as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour ſhall deſire and need, both for his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſervice, as alſo for all other Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to carry their Baggage and other Goods as farre as <hi>Mechlen;</hi> amongſt which are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all manner of Weapons, both of the gariſon Souldiers, abſent, dead, ſicke, wounded, and of thoſe that ranne away; and that the aforenamed Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons ſhall not be ſearched in any wiſe.</p>
            <p n="7">VII That ſuch as deſire to have their Baggage and Goods carryed by water to <hi>Mechlen,</hi> ſhall be provided with fitting Bottoms for their convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19206:3"/>thither through <hi>Holland,</hi> unleſſe it be any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Wares. And that there ſhall likewiſe bee granted unto them, to ſend along certaine men that may looke to the Goods and Baggage, which ſhall not be ſearched nor arreſted in any places under what pretence ſoever it may be, but ſhall paſſe ſafely as farre as <hi>Mechlen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">VIII That the Governour, Captaines, Officers, Counſellers of warre, and Souldiers taking pay of the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> (aſwell Temporall as Spirituall perſons, none excepted) as alſo the widowes with their children, which in the afore ſaid city have any Houſes, Inheritance or Rents, whether it lie under the States of <hi>Brabant</hi> in this quarter, or under this city, houſes or inheritances of particular Goods, moveable or immoveable, ſhall enjoy the time of 2 yeres after the ſealing of this Accord, to tranſport, ſell, remove, or diſpoſe otherwiſe of their Goods, according to their will and pleaſure; and during the time, they ſhall enjoy their Rents, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of the hire of their houſes, and have the fruits of their Goods, which they expect, or may expect, upon the Conditions agreed of, whatever they be.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. That the Officers and Souldiers, of what condition or ſtate ſoever they be, ſhall have licence to leave their Wives and Children in the City, and that they may, during the time of 2. yeeres, diſpoſe of their Goods moveable or immoveable, whether they lie within or without the ſaid City, nothing excepted, and that they ſhall neither bee confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nor detained from them.</p>
            <p n="10">X. None of the Officers or Souldiers in perſon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19206:4"/>ſhall be arreſted or ſtayed, whether preſent or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming for the Rents of their houſes where they dwelled, neither their Baggage ſtaied for any debts, if they depart with the gariſon.</p>
            <p n="11">XI That all the Souldiers which are taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, aſwel by one as byth' other ſide, of what qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or dignity ſoever they be, ſhall be ſet at liberty without paying of any ranſome, but ſhall ohely pay for their diet according to the taxation of the Quarter: As alſo Preachers and other priſoners ſhall goe out paying onely for their diets.</p>
            <p n="12">XII That all the Booty which they have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before and during the ſiege, ſhall not bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of them, but be left to them.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII That after the ſubſcription, and ſealing of the Articles of this agreement, the Governor of <hi>Breda</hi> ſhall have licence to ſend un Expreſſe to His Highneſſe the Cardinal <hi>Infant,</hi> with a ſafe conduct and aſſecuration to certifie him of it, what hath paſſed during the time of the ſiege, which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour may doe the ſame day when the Accord is ſubſcribed.</p>
            <p n="14">XIIII The ſaid Conditions being ſubſcribed and ſealed, at leaſt a dayes reſpit ſhall be granted unto the Governour and Souldiers to make themſelves ready againſt their departure; which time being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, the Governour and Officers of the ſaid gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall promiſe to depart, namely, upon Saturday following, being the 30. of <hi>Septem.</hi> no of <hi>Oct.</hi> 1637.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. The meaning of the former Article is; that none afore the 2. dayes are expired, ſhall come out of the City into our Camp, neither that thoſe of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19206:4"/>our army ſhall come into the city; and to prevent all diſorders, every one ſhall keep in his trenches and for tiſications, except perhaps one ſide or other ſhould offer to make any approaches, or do any hoſtility, for the aſſecuration whereof Hoſtages ſhall be given of both ſides.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. That before the gariſon departeth two ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Hoſtages ſhall be delivered, as pledges for his Highneſſe, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who ſhall march a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with the garriſon as farre as <hi>Mechelen,</hi> and that on the other ſide, two Hoſtages ſhall be left by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, ſo long till the aforeſaid Hoſtages of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> are returned backe againe with the weapons, and that then his Highneſſe the Prince ſhal likewiſe ſend again the two aforeſaid Hoſtages of the Governour with a ſafe conduct or convoy, as farre as <hi>Mechelen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">XVII. That the Officers and Souldiers, and others comprehended in the firſt article of the aforeſaid accord, having any Armour, boats, Shaloopes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther materials of warre belonging to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, may ſell or tranſport them, and that they ſhall not be ſtay'd or any wares or goods, that are bought or are tranſported upon them.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. And that there ſhall be no reſtitution of horſes, amongſt merchants wares, moveable goods or other wares, which are ſould and held for a bootie, and that becauſe of them none ſhall be ſtay'd or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Actum</hi> in the Campe before Breda, <date>the 27 of September, the 7 of October, 1637.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="declarations_regarding_articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:19206:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19206:5"/>
            <head>A Copie of the Articles propounded by the Clergie and the Burgermaſters, Sheriffs and Senate of the City of <hi>Breda,</hi> to His Highnes the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Lord and Baron of <hi>Breda.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>His Highnes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeen and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the Articles, here ſtanding by hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelfe upon it in this manner.</head>
            <p n="1">I THat all faults, Hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and miſdeeds, how great and of what quality ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they may be (without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any perſon, Churchman, or Layman; of the aforeſaid Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, committed by them either preſent or abſent; whether it be in generall or particular) ſhall fully be forgotten and pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as if they never had been done or committed.</p>
            <p n="1" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">I THis Article is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, if ſo bee that all the perſons mentioned in it do behave themſelves hereafter, as they ought to do.</p>
            <p n="2">II That in the aforeſaid City of <hi>Breda,</hi> now and ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be granted free and open exerciſe of the Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion in the great Church, in the Cloyſters and Nunneries; as it hath been thoſe 12. yeeres laſt paſt in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: That no man of what qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19206:6"/>ſoever he be, whether Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill or Military, ſhall undertake to offer or do any hinderance, obſtacle or ſcandall in the Church or in the ſtreet; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in words or deeds upon paine of arbitrary correction.</p>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19206:5"/>
            <p n="2" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">II That two Cloyſters of Nunnes and <hi>Bagynes</hi> ſhall be maintained in the ſame manner, as they have been before the yeere 1625. in the time of the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords States Generall.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19206:6"/>
            <p n="3">III That the Magiſtrate ſhall be choſen out of all perſons, indifferently as well of the Romane Catholike, as refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion.</p>
            <p n="3" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">III That the Magiſtrate ſhall be choſen of the beſt qualified perſons of the City according to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and Lawes of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant,</hi> and of the aforeſaid City of <hi>Breda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IIII That the Lords of the Chapiter with their Subpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſts, Provoſt and Nunnery of Saint <hi>Catharine Dale,</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, the College of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of JESUS, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents of the <hi>Patres Capucyns,</hi> and Minorites, and all other ſpirituall perſons, of what ſtate or order ſoever they be; which afore the date of thoſe Articles have been accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and placed, ſhall continue in a peaceable poſſeſſion of all manner of goods, Rents, gifts, Tithes, privileges and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes whatſoever they be; as well within as without the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſaid City without exception to place new ones, or ſurrogate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19206:6"/>others: but poſſeſſe them in the ſame manner as they all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one keep, poſſeſſe and uſe them now without any let, hinderance, or harme: and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Canons, places or Benefices ſhall come to be void, they ſhall be given to the Romane Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks, according to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations and ancient Statutes.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19206:6"/>
            <p n="4" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">
               <hi>IIII</hi> That all Spirituall perſons may have the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit &amp; uſe of their goods, and adminiſtrate them, in the ſame manner as they have done before the yeere 1625. Thoſe that depart out of the City ſhall freely take along with them their goods and movables, as alſo, if they be houſes or lands, they may ſell them like the Citizens.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19206:6"/>
            <p n="5">V The yeerely revenewes of the goods and lands of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane-houſe in the aforeſaid City, Whether it be by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance or donation; which it hath already attained, or ſhall attain unto hereafter, whether it be by ſervice, gift, purchaſe, or any otherwiſe, ſhall be divided <hi>prorato</hi> and proportionally, that the poore children, of what Religion ſoever they be found; ſhall likewiſe have their Maſters and dwellings apart: And goods, almes and collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Hoſpitall or Almes-houſe called the Holy-Ghoſt, ſhall be adminiſtred and divided by perſons amongſt the poore, without regard of what Religion they are, as it hath bin done hitherto.</p>
            <p n="5" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">V That the goods, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, Almes of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective poore houſes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in this Article, ſhall be uſed and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, as they have been before the yeere 1625. without regard to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the perſons, which are employed in that behalfe.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19206:7"/>
            <p n="6">VI That the City of <hi>Breda</hi> and all its Inhabitants ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue all their priviledges and liberties, and that no further burthens ſhall be laid upon them, then there have been from the yeere 1590. till unto the yeere 1625. ſo long as the City was under the government of the united Nether-lands: and being their City by this ſiege is exceedingly ruinated, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that they might be free of the Licents for 3. yeeres to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves againe.</p>
            <p n="6" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">VI His Highneſſe grants this Article, but what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the point of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, He will recommend it in the beſt manner to the Lords States Generall.</p>
            <p n="7">VII That all the Citizens and Inhabitants of the aforeſaid Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whether preſent or abſent, of what quality ſoever they be, whether they have been in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> or no, may freely according to this treaty depart and go whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they pleaſe with their whole family and moveable goods, and papers; or that they may continue in their dwelling places in the aforeſaid City, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſpace of a ſet time, that within that ſpace they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, whether they wil ſtay and dwell there longer or no; and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19206:7"/>
that during the ſaid time they may ſafely and freely travaile up and down in the Countrey, as well to provide where to pitch their dwelling places, as for their particular affaires and buſines for the ſpace of 4. yeers, and if in the end of the ſet time they intend to depart, they may likewiſe do it freely with their Wives, Children and goods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they pleaſe by water or land without paying of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Licents or ſearching of the Ships; although one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had done any publike ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the aforenamed 4. yeers; and they ſhall have leave to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of all their goods, ſel them, tranſport them, or appoint o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to receive and adminiſter them, as they think fitteſt: and if it come to paſſe that they die, whether it be within or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the City, whether He make his laſt wil or no, the ſaid goods are to belong to the lawfull heires, or their next friends <hi>ab inteſtato reſpectivè</hi> and they may carry away all their moveable goods, merchants wares and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goods, as they think beſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19206:8"/>without requiring any other Paſſe then this preſent treatie: and thoſe that go into Neutral Countries, if they pleaſe, they may return back againe into the City to dwell there without deſiring of any further conſent.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19206:7"/>
            <p n="7" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">VII His Highneſſe gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this Petition for the ſpace of three yeeres in particular, alſo for the fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, with condition; that thoſe which intend to goe into Neutral places, or into the flat Country, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards will return againe into the City, they ſhall be bound to do it with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent knowledge of His Highnes or of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19206:8"/>
            <p n="8">VIII That thoſe, which for their particular affaires will go into the Countries and Cities under the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> may have leave to do it during the time of the aforeſaid 4. yeeres, as often as they pleaſe, and may alwaies return againe into the ſaid City to ſtay and to dwell there, or to depart as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="8" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">
               <hi>VIII</hi> They may depart, during the time of three yeeres into the enemies Countries or Cities; and may return againe into <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> yet not without a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent conſent of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour.</p>
            <p n="9">IX In the aforeſaid contract ſhall be comprehended all Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and Inhabitants of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid City, which are abſent, as alſo all Paſtors and ſpirituall perſons, which are fled into the City; as alſo the Inhabitants which are fled from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try into the City, which by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this Contract may freely returne to their Villages and dwellings, or ſtay in the City the aforeſaid 4. yeeres, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they pleaſe: and the Paſtors of the Baronie of <hi>Breda</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19206:8"/>preſent or abſent, and their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors may exerciſe againe in their Pariſh Churches their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall ſervices, and keep the revenewes, as they had before the <hi>Retorſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19206:8"/>
            <p n="9" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">IX This Article is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo farre, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the Citizens, but the Paſtors and other Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall perſons mentioned in this Article, may well depart out of the City, but regulate themſelves according to the Patents of Retorſion publiſhed by the Lords States.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19206:8"/>
            <p n="10">X That all the Sentences gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Magiſtrate of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid City, and by the Head-Bench, wherof nothing was yet reformed, ſhall remain in their full force; as alſo all contracts made before and in the time of the ſiege howſoever they be.</p>
            <p n="10" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">X This Article is granted as it ſtands.</p>
            <p n="11">XI That all the perfected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of the City, as alſo all others that are done by the Magiſtrate, ſhall remain entire and ſtand in force.</p>
            <p n="11" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">XI This Article is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe granted as it ſtands, if ſo be that all Charters, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters and Papers, Feods, Dominions, as alſo others, whether they be ſpirituall or temporall goods, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning His Highnes, be put into the hands of thoſe, that His Highnes ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point.</p>
            <p n="12">XII That thoſe which have Rents or debts depending upon the Citie, ſhall yearly be payd without abatement, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe avoyding them.</p>
            <p n="12" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">
               <hi>XII</hi> This in like manner.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII That the City of <hi>Breda</hi> ſhall not be bound to make, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire and ſupport the Walls, Forts, Gates, Bridges, <hi>Corps de guards,</hi> and other Fortifications and Workes; they having been freed of it theſe laſt 12. yeares under the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">
               <hi>XIII</hi> Thoſe of the City of <hi>Breda</hi> ſhal behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this as they have before the yeere 1625.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19206:9"/>
            <p n="14">XIIII That the Souldier and Garriſon, which ſhall be layd into the ſaid City; as well foot as horſe, or ſhall be lodged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Baruques, or in any other manner, ſhall not be burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the City or the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens: and if ſo be that any Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier ſhould be Billited in the Citizens houſes, they ſhall be payd for their ſervices.</p>
            <p n="14" rend="small" ana="#role_commentary">
               <hi>XIIII</hi> The Souldiers ſhall be Billited like as in other Cities of the united Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces is done.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Actum</hi> in the Campe before <hi>Breda,</hi> 
                  <date>the 7. of October, 1637.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hampt. court</hi> 
                  <date>15. <hi>of Octob.</hi> 1637.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Theſe Articles of <hi>Breda</hi> may be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. WECHERLIN.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19206:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
